Alexander **Fred-Ojala**

EMERGING TECHNOLOGY · ENTREPRENEURSHIP · RESEARCH / EDUCATION

2724 Derby st. Berkeley, CA 94705, USA

□ (+1) 510-993-6337 | 🗷 afo@berkeley.edu | 🔏 alex.fo | 🖸 afo | 🛅 alexanderfo | 💆 @alexanderfo

Summary_

AI, Data Science, and Blockchain expert. Research Director and Instructor at UC Berkeley, the #1 Public University in the world. Startup founder with an entrepreneurial mindset. I help industry leaders benefit from the true potential of emerging technologies.

Work Experience __

Sutardja Center for Entrepreneurship & Technology, UC Berkeley

Berkeley, CA, USA

CHIEF DATA SCIENTIST & RESEARCH DIRECTOR

Aug. 2017 - Present

- · Research and teaching related to the application of emerging technologies. Manage AI and blockchain industry collaborations.
- Co-founder of the Data Lab and the Blockchain Lab
- Technical Manager, the Blockchain Xcelerator Spring 2019.
- Project Manager and Lead Data Scientist of the global research project The Berkeley Innovation Index
- Websites: scet.berkeley.edu/data-lab || scet.berkeley.edu/blockchain-lab || berkeleyinnovationindex.org

College of Engineering, UC Berkeley

Berkeley, CA, USA

INSTRUCTOR & PROGRAM DIRECTOR

Oct 2016 - Present

- Instructor and co-creator of IEOR135 / IEOR 290 Applied Data Science with Venture Applications (800+ students, 200+ open-ended data science projects completed
- Technical Program Director and Instructor, Learn2Launch (through Haas Business School). Blockchain curriculum creator.
- Instructor and co-creator of IEOR 185 Blockchain Challenge Lab, Fall 2018
- Websites: data-x.blog || learn2launch.berkeley.edu || ieor.github.io/blockchain185

San Francisco & Stockholm, SWE

Predli

May 2019 - Present

· Predli is an emerging technology expertise advisory firm. We advise companies on AI and Blockchain strategies. www.predli.com

InnoQuant San Francisco, CA, USA

CO-FOUNDER & COO

FOUNDER & CEO

Feb 2017 - June 2018

• Created a fully automated innovation assessment tool to help companies improve their innovation capability. Revenue positive, 15k+ users. www.berkeleyinnovationindex.com

Auranest Inc. Lund Sweden

CMO & FOUNDING TEAM

Jan 2014 - Jan 2016

· First employee of this jobtech startup. Manager and head of team. Raised two investment rounds and won several awards. www.auranest.com

Education

UC Berkeley Berkeley, CA, USA

M.Sc. Mathematical Statistics \parallel GPA: 4.0 / 4.0

Lund University & Uppsala University

Aug 2015 - Oct 2016

- Graduate Studies in the Department of Mathematics / Statistics: Data Science, Applied Mathematics, and Entrepreneurship.
- Thesis: Construction of the Berkeley Innovation Index A Higher Order Item Response Theory Approach

Lund University Lund, Sweden

M.Sc. Mathematical Statistics and Financial Modeling | GPA: 5.0 / 5.0

Aug 2014 - Sept 2016

• Awarded: LU's Education Abroad stipend, the Anna Whitlock Foundation stipend, Hakon Hansson's stipend, Crafoordska Stiftelsen's stipend.

Lund & Uppsala, Sweden

B.Sc. Engineering Physics | Minor in Macroeconomics || GPA: 4.7 / 5.0

Aug 2009 - May 2013

- Teaching Assistant: Calculus and Linear Algebra 2011-2014. Hosted teaching sessions for 30+ engineering students 2 times per week and corrected university exams.
- Awarded: The Hilbert Scholarship, Teacher of the Year Award, AF's stipend, Krischansta nation's scholarship, Dagny & Eilert Ekwall's scholarship.

CV · ALEXANDER FRED-OJALA 1ST OCTOBER 2019

Program Committees

2019 -	Visiting Professor, Plaksha University, Implementation and instructor of the data science curriculum.	New Delhi, India
2018 -	Industry Fellow - HKBU Business Entrepreneurship Support and Training, Entrepreneurship and	Hong Kong
	innovation community hosted at Hong Kong Baptist University	
2018 -	Board Member, Muovitech AB , The Largest manufacturer of Geothermal Products in Europe with over 100	Sweden
	employees in eight countries	
2015	Chairman of the Nominations Committee, Brygghuset FINN, Elected the new Board	Sweden
2014	Industry Mentor, Forsberg's School, Mentored Johan Bylund's examination project.	Sweden

Published Papers & Articles ____

- **1** Bathia, S., Castro-Hernandez, E., Goyal, M., & **Fred-Ojala**, **A.** (2019). Comparative analysis of innovation capability: Examining differences across career strata and gender using item response theory. *ICE IEEE Nice*, *France*.
- 2 Tsang, N., Cao, C., & **Fred-Ojala**, **A.** (2019). Autonomous Household Energy Consumption using Deep Reinforcement Learning. *ICE IEEE Nice*, *France*.
- **Fred-Ojala**, **A.**, Sidhu, I., & Charlotta, J. (2018). A quantitative approach to measure, track and forecast innovation capability within individuals and organizations. *ICIMSA Hong Kong*.
- 4 Sidhu, I., Ferry, T., & **Fred-Ojala**, **A.** (2018). Breaking the Zuckerberg myth: Successful entrepreneurs have 10 years of prior employment. *ICE IEEE Stuttgart, Germany*.
- 5 Sidhu, I. & **Fred-Ojala**, **A.** (2018a). Applying entrepreneurial teaching methods to advanced technical STEM courses. *ICE IEEE Stuttgart*, *Germany*.
- 6 Sidhu, I. & Fred-Ojala, A. (2018b). The future of Blockchain A Berkeley perspective. *College of Engineering, UCB*.
- **Fred-Ojala**, **A.** & Eng Larsson, J. (2016). *Construction of the Berkeley Innovation Index: A higher-order item response theory model approach*. Master Thesis.
- 8 Sidhu, I., **Fred-Ojala**, **A.**, & et al. (2016). *Berkeley Innovation Index: An approach for measuring and diagnosing individual's and organizations' innovation capabilities*. Berkeley Electronic Press.

Selected Presentations & Keynotes _____

Sept 2019 Keynote , Industrial Applications of AI, PiiA	Stockholm, Sweden
Sept 2019 Keynote , Al Business Models, Hightech Summit	Stuttgart, Germany
May 2019 Keynote , Blockchain in Silicon Valley, Asian Leadership Conference	Seoul, South Korea
Feb 2019 Keynote , Blockchain in Practice, United Arab Emirates University	Dubai, UAE
Nov 2018 Distinguished Guest Lecture, Data Science, Hamad Bin Khalifa University	Doha, Qatar
Oct 2018 Keynote , Blockchain & Cryptocurrencies for Taiwan Delegation	Berkeley, USA
Oct 2018 Main Speaker, Mastercard Innovation Session	San Francisco, USA
May 2018 Opening Speaker , TiE Inflect: Blockchain Bootcamp	Santa Clara, USA
May 2018 Keynote Speaker & Mentor, Berkeley Method of Entrepreneurship Bootcamp	HKBU, Hong Kong
Apr 2018 Keynote , UC Berkeley, College of Engineering: Showcase to Donors	Berkeley, USA
Nov 2017 Panelist & Innovation Expert, Tech Match Malaysia	San Mateo, USA
Oct 2017 Keynote , Innovation in Silicon Valley: Delegation Visit from China's National Statistics Bureau	Berkeley, USA

Honors & Awards _____

2018 -	Amazon Alexa Innovation Fellow, Ten leading university faculty members in applied AI were awarded the	Coattle IICA
	Innovation Fellowship.	Seattle, USA
2015-2016	UC Berkeley Exchange Scholar , I received the opportunity to complete my Master's at UC Berkeley	Sweden
2014	Auranest, 2nd Place, Venture Cup, The World's Largest Business Plan Competition	Sweden
2013	Auranest, Top 50 Most Innovative Startups, ACE Europe	Brussels, Belgium
2013	Student Teacher of the Year, Lund University	Sweden



Programming Python, R, Spark, Java, Solidity, Matlab, Bash

Web React, Javascript, CSS, Flask, HTML5

Cloud AWS, GCP

 $\textbf{Misc} \hspace{0.3cm} \textbf{SQL, Git, Jupyter, Databricks, Excel, } \textbf{ET}_{E\!X}$

Languages Swedish (native), English (fluent), Spanish (beginner)Interests Yoga, Tennis, Art, Running, Climbing, Music, and Writing.